Gardner, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1786-2023. RG5486
Congregational Library & Archives
Gardner, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1786-2023.
Congregational Library & Archives
First Congregational Church (Gardner, Mass.)
RG5486
6.98 Cubic Feet (7 boxes)
In February 1786, thirty-three members would form the First Congregational Church of Gardner, led by town physician Rev. Jonathan Osgood. In 1830, there was a split in the congregation which resulted in a separate, Evangelical Church. They would form together again in 1846, adopting the creed of the Evangelical Church. In the 1880s, the church started to take part in the Christian Endeavor movement and the Young Ladies' Missionary Society began teaching English to the rising population of non-English speakers in Gardner. In the 1950s, Rev. Daniel Leavitt would arrive and breathe new life into the church, including modernizing the Parish House and renovating many of its features. The church would make the decision to close for good in 2023. This collection contains various records related to the entire history of the First Congregational Church. This includes meeting minutes, annual reports, auxiliary groups, vital statistics, photographs, scrapbooks, and building records.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational & Library and Archives by the First Congregational Church in October 2023, 2023-52.
Historical Note
The town of Gardner, Mass, was incorporated in June of 1785 and four months later at the third town meeting, talks began to start building a meeting-house. In February of 1786, thirty-three members would form the First Congregational Church of Gardner. The first meeting-house would be raised on June 27, 1787. The first minister, who also happened to be the first physician of Gardner, was Dr. Jonathan Osgood. Dr. Osgood would remain a central part of the church and the town of Gardner until his death in 1822.
Starting around 1830, a divide started to form that would be common in many other areas of the country. More liberal minded members would begin to call themselves Unitarian while the more conservative called themselves Orthodox. The orthodox members, alongside the current minister Rev. Increase Summer Lincoln, would form the Evangelical Congregational Church. Both groups did agree to share many items needed for worship and equally divided what money was on hand at the time.
First Congregational Church would see increased membership over the next decade and in 1846, the church would reunite with the Evangelical Congregational Church. They kept the First Congregational Church name, the creed of the Evangelical Church, and worshipped in the Evangelical Church's building. A parsonage was built in 1875 and a brand-new church was dedicated in 1879. In the 1880s the church started to take part in the Christian Endeavor movement and the Young Ladies' Missionary Society began teaching English to the rising population of non-English speakers in Gardner.
Rev. Burton S. Gilman would serve as the pastor from 1897-1920 and was known as an eloquent and convincing speaker, loved amongst the community. After a series of short-lived pastorates, Rev. Baldwin W. Callahan would lead the church up through 1949. Under his pastorate, the Evening Guild, Men's Club, and Married Couples' Group would form, and the Woman's Association would form out of two previously separate groups. In the 1950s, Rev. Daniel Leavitt would arrive and breathe new life into the church, including modernizing the Parish House and renovating many of its features.
The church would continue to engage in its works and mission and led by ministers such as Rev John Condor, Rev. Edgar Kemp, Jr., Rev. Frank McKenzie and more. The church would make the decision to close for good in 2023. At its final service on October 1st, they were led by transitional minister Rev. Stacey Kullgren. The history of the First Congregational Church is entwined with the history of Gardner and its impact will always be felt.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains various records related to the entire history of the First Congregational Church. This includes meeting minutes, annual reports, auxiliary groups, vital statistics, photographs, scrapbooks, and building records.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the six series and seven subseries as listed below. Within each series and subseries, materials have been arranged in chronological order. When appropriate, some material is arranged by topic.
Series 1: Church records, 1786-2022
Subseries 1: Meeting minutes and reports, 1786-2022
Subseries 2: Newsletters, 1894, 1957-1968
Subseries 3: History and Events, 1936-2008, undated
Series 2: Ministerial records, 1847-2023
Series 3: Auxiliary groups, 1848-2010
Subseries 1: Women's Groups, 1848-1975
Subseries 2: Educational Groups, 1886-2010
Subseries 3: Massachusetts Conference records, 1905-1999
Subseries 4: Diaconate records, 1967-2006
Series 4: Vital Statistics, 1862-2020
Series 5: Visual material, 1883-1961, undated
Series 6: Building records, 1890-2011
Vital statistics.; Church newsletters.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Women in church work.; Christian education of children.; Church correspondence.; Clergy -- Appointment, call, and election.; Deacons -- Congregational churches.; First Congregational Church (Gardner, Mass.); Gardner (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Church records, 1786-2022; 46 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains information related to church records and includes meeting minutes, reports, historical information, events, and newsletters.
  - Meeting minutes and reports, 1786-2022; 31 Folders
    This subseries contains meeting minutes are reports related to core operations of the First Congregational Church. These include annual reports, church meeting minutes, treasurer's reports, church correspondences, board of Trustees meeting minutes, church council meeting minutes, and more.
    - Church meeting minutes, 1786-1857 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Treasurer's reports and records, 1896-1919 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Calls for meetings, 1900-1910 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Parish committee meeting minutes, 1906-1925 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Prudential committee meeting minutes, 1916-1921 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Church records (book 2), 1922-1937 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Church clerk correspondences, 1923-1931 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Organizational reports, 1937-1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Annual reports, 1938-1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - UCC presents "Our Church", September 12, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Annual report, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Church records (book 4), 1966-2009 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1967-1971 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Various church correspondences, 1968-1980 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Annual reports, 1972-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Various church correspondences, 1973-2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Census report, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Long range planning committee, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Annual reports, 1982-1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Clerk's reports, 1988-1997 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Annual reports, 1992-2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Special committee to address church concerns, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Safe church policy draft, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Annual reports, 2005-2012 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Annual reports, 2013-2022 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Church council meeting minutes, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Church council meeting minutes, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Church council meeting minutes, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Church council meeting minutes, 2018-2019 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Church council meeting minutes, 2020-2022 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1952-1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1959-1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes (1 of 2), 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes (2 of 2), 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 2018-2019 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Values and faith evaluation, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Newsletters, 1894, 1957-1968; 4 Folders
    This subseries contains newsletters produced by the First Congregational Church, including the Gardner journal, the Tower Times, and Tidings.
    - Gardner journal, 1894 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - The Tower Times newsletter, 1957-1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - The Tower Times newsletter, 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Tidings newsletter, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - History and Events, 1936-2008, undated; 11 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to events and the history of the First Congregational Church, including constitution and bylaws, a church times, and records related to church anniversaries.
    - Celebration of the 150th anniversary, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Constitution and by-laws, 1951-1954 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Gardner tercentenary program, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Affiliation with the UCC, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Forbearer's Day, June 1979 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Bicentennial committee, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - 200th anniversary, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Church by-laws, 2003-2007 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Church timeline, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - The Church Raising: a play, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Survey on the history of Gardner, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Ministerial records, 1847-2023; 31 Folders
  This series contains records related to the many ministers of First Congregational Church and includes correspondences, sermons, call agreements, and information on the final service of the church.
  - Pastoral calls and resignations, 1847-1897 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Biography of Rev. Burton Smith Gilman, 1849-1864 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sermons (1 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sermons (2 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sermons (3 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sermons (4 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sermons (5 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sermons (6 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sermons (7 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sermons (8 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sermons (9 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Sermons (10 of 10), 1896,1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - A sermon on hope by Rev. Burton Smith Gilman, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Various sermons, 1904-1905 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Nomination committee records, 1933-1936 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Rev. Edward Barry records, 1956-1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Rev. Daniel Leavitt records, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Sermons in living glass, February 14, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - God's gift and out response - a sermon in five parts, August 1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rev. John Condon records, 1972-1983 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Rev. Baldwin Callahan records, 1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Interim pastoral records, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Rev. Sandra Hartman records, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Rev. Edgar Kemp, Jr. records, 1988-1992 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Rev. Charles B. Mansfield records, 1991-2001 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Rev. Janet Skagerlind call agreement, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Rev. Francis McKenzie call agreement, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Rev. Holly MillerShank call agreement, 2017 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Karen Hodges call agreement, 2017 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Final worship, October 1, 2023 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Hymns and prayers, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Auxiliary groups, 1848-2010; 55 Folders
  This series contains various records related to various auxiliary groups from the First Congregational Church, including educational groups, Women's groups, the Massachusetts Conference, and from the Diaconate.
  - Women's Groups, 1848-1975; 21 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to various Women's groups part of the First Congregational Church, including the Ladies' social circle, Ladies' sewing society, Women's fellowship, Women's missionary society, Women's missionary society and Women's Association.
    - Ladies' social circle records, 1902-1911 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ladies' social and benevolent circle treasurer's reports, 1910-1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Ladies' social circle records, 1911-1922 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Ladies' social circle records, 1921-1931 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Ladies' sewing society records, 1848-1866 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Ladies' sewing society records, 1870-1880 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Ladies' sewing society records, 1886-1898 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Women's Fellowship reports, 1956-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Women's Fellowship records (1 of 3), 1963-1975 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Women's Fellowship records (2 of 3), 1963-1975 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Women's Fellowship records (3 of 3), 1963-1975 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Women's Missionary Society records (1 of 4), 1880-1889 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Women's Missionary Society records (2 of 4), 1880-1889 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Women's Missionary Society records (3 of 4), 1880-1889 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Women's Missionary Society records (4 of 4), 1880-1889 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Auxiliary Women Board of Missions finances, 1896-1912 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Home Department of the Women's Missionary Society reports, 1902-1916 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Women's Missionary Society records, 1922-1931 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Women's Missionary Society finances, 1924-1931 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Women's Association menu book, 1931-1942 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Women's Association record book, 1949-1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Educational Groups, 1886-2010; 20 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the various educational groups of the First Congregational Church, including the Christian Endeavor meeting minutes, Bible study, Sunday School, Christian education society, Fellowship committee, and more.
    - Christian endeavor records, 1886-1896 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Christian endeavor membership and by-laws, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Christian endeavor records, 1896-1906 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Christian endeavor records, 1904-1911 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Christian endeavor meeting minutes, 1906-1911 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Christian endeavor records (1 of 2), 1920-1925 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Christian endeavor records (2 of 2), 1920-1925 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Christian endeavor meeting minutes, 1925-1931 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Christian endeavor meeting minutes, 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Christian endeavor membership and by-laws, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Bible study department, 1903-1908 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Sunday school reports, 1906-1913 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Young people's society records, 1930-1934 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Church school council secretary's minutes, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Music committee records, 1965-1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Grace A. Howe sacred concert series, 1978-1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Mission council meeting minutes, 2003-2005 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Christian education meeting minutes, 2003-2006 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Fellowship committee meeting minutes, 2004-2006 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Fellowship committee meeting minutes, 2006-2010 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Massachusetts Conference records, 1905-1999; 7 Folders
    This subseries contains records relating to interactions between the Massachusetts Conference and the First Congregational Church, including meeting minutes, yearbook applications, and annual reports
    - Yearbook applications, 1905-1943 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Massachusetts Congregational Conference at First Congregational Church, May 1936 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Yearbook applications, 1945-1999 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Central Association of Massachusetts Conference records (1 of 2), 1965-1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Central Association of Massachusetts Conference records (2 of 2), 1965-1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Massachusetts Conference records, 1968-1988 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Central Association of Massachusetts Conference annual reports, 1977-1980, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Diaconate records, 1967-2006; 7 Folders
    This subseries contains meeting minutes and reports from both Deacons and Deaconesses.
    - Board of deacons' reports, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Deacon and Deaconess meeting minutes, 1964-1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Diaconate meeting minutes, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Diaconate meeting minutes, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Deacons' workshop, October 26, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Diaconate meeting minutes, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Deacon meeting minutes, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Vital Statistics, 1862-2020; 33 Folders
  This series contains various vital statistics from the First Congregational Church and includes baptisms, deaths, marriages, membership, letters of dismission, and letters of transfer.
  - Baptism lists, 1905-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baptisms, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baptisms, 1980-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baptisms, 2003-2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Baptisms, 2011-2014 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Baptisms, 2015-2019 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Death records, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deaths, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Deaths, 1999-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deaths, 2006-2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Deaths, 2015-2018 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Death notices, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Marriages, 1900, 1980-2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Marriages, 2005-2007 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Marriages, 2008-2020 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters of dismission, 1893-1937 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters of dismission, 1909-1920 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters of dismission, 1920-1928 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Memberships, 2005-2018 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondences related to membership, 1862-1915 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Church records and membership, 1867-1880 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Living members who joined from 1920-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - List of service members, September 18, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Church sign-in book, 1947-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Church sign-in book, 1948-2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Vital statistics, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Church meeting minutes and membership, 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Yearbook and directories, 1958, 1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Membership and transfers, 1962-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Resident membership lists, 1970-1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Resident membership mailing list, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Membership committee reports (1 of 2), 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Membership committee reports (2 of 2), 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Visual material, 1883-1961, undated; 4 Folders
  The series contains visual materials like photographs and scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbook, 1883-1985 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Scrapbook on church visit to Puerto Rico, 1939-1961 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Assorted photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Assorted photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Building records, 1890-2011; 13 Folders
  This series contains records related to the operation of the church building and includes renovation material, inventories, alterations, maintenance, and more.
  - Building records, 1890-1972 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Swedish match stocks, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Six year plan, January 1954 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Memorial fund, 1957-1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Alterations to the First Congregational Church, September 19, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Renovations, 1958-1966 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Audits, 1965-1973 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Church inventories, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Handbell choir records, 1985-1993 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Parish planning inventory, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Building maintenance records, 2010-2011 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Symbols in our sanctuary, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Preparations and guidelines for church events, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)